A Guide to the Warren County (Va.) Circuit Court Records, 1836-1924
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Warren County (Va.) Circuit Court Records, 1836-1924
The Library of Virginia
1013618-1096595 circa
2.1 cu. ft. (6 boxes) and 17 volumes.
Warren County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in a shipment of court papers from Warren County.
Historical Information
Warren County was named for Joseph Warren, the revolutionary patriot who sent Paul Revere and William Dawes on their famous rides and who was killed at the Battle of Bunker Hill. The county was formed from Frederick and Shenandoah counties in 1836.
A Docket is a brief record of proceedings in a court of justice. It usually gives the style of the suit and the date the court first dealt with it. Sometime it gives the date the suit was removed from the docket.
An execution is a court order directing a sheriff or other officer to enforce a judgment, usually by seizing and selling the judgment debtor's property. An Execution Books lists executions sued out or pending in the sheriff's office. It shows notices of process, names of all parties, amount of judgment, date of execution, return date and sheriff's return.
An issue is the act of issuing or promulgating; e.g. to issue an order or writ. An issue docket is the record of issuance, showing parties' names, actions, and remarks.
Fee Books are volumes showing the date of a duty performed by the clerk, the name of the person paying the fees, and the amount. It includes the fees charged attorneys, cash accounts, and the clerk's fees in common law and chancery cause.
Rules Books contain the records of the session of Court where complainant(s) began the process to have a suit heard in court. For the first session of Rule, the complainant(s) appeared at court and gave information of who he wanted to sue and why. The court issued a subpoena to the defendant(s) giving the date they were to appear at court to answer a Bill exhibited against them. Some suits did not make it out of the Rule Sessions because, the plaintiff did not file a Bill, he asked the court to dismiss his Bill, or he did not prosecute the Bill. If the plaintiff did not provide a security to pay for the cost of court, his suit was dismissed in Rules. When the plaintiff or defendant died while the suit was still in Rules, the Rule of Abatement caused the suit to end. If the plaintiff met all the requirements for a Bill to be heard in Court, the Bill and other suit documents were sent to the appropriate court to be heard.
Scope and Content
Warren County (Va.) Circuit Court Records, 1836-1924 contains Executions, Executions Returned, Issue Dockets, Chancery Issue Dockets, Chancery Rule Book B, Witness Attendance Book, Receiver's Books, Common Law Issues, Execution Book, Fee Books and Chancery Fee Book.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Warren County Court Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm"
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Warren County (Va.) Circuit Court
Subjects:
Circuit courts--Virginia; Court records--Virginia--Warren County
Geographical Names:
Warren County (Va.)--History
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records--Virginia--Warren County; Judicial records--Virginia--Warren County; Public records--Virginia--Warren County
Contents List
- Executions Returned, 1836-1860
  Barcode Number 1013622 contains Executions Returned, 1836-1860, Box 232. Barcode Number 1013618 contains Executions Returned, 1841-1844, Box 233.
- Executions, 1852-1892
  Barcode Number 1013626 contains Executions, 1852-1886, Box 238. Barcode Number 1013624 contains Executions, 1859-1869, Box 240. Barcode Number 1013623 contains Executions, 1869-1872, Box 241. Barcode Number 1013629 contains Executions, 1872-1892, Box 242.
- Issue Dockets, 1852-1880
  Barcode Number 1096414 contains Issue Docket, 1852-1871. Barcode Number 1096408 contains Issue Docket, 1871-1880.
- Chancery Issue Docket, 1873-1895
  Barcode Number 1096409 contains Chancery Issue Docket, 1873-1875. Barcode Number 1096410 contains Chancery Issue Docket, 1876-1878. Barcode Number 1096411 contains Chancery Issue Docket, 1879-1883. Barcode Number 1096412 contains Chancery Issue Docket, 1884-1895.
- Chancery Issue Docket, 1896
  This book contains issues made for Chancery Causes.
- Chancery Rule Book B, 1879-1914
  This book is a list of causes hear in the Rules session of the Court.
- Witness Attendance Book, 1871-1887
  This book contains the names of the witness called to appear at court for judgments, criminal cases, and or chancery causes.
- Receiver's Books, 1851-1896
  Barcode Number 1096541 contains Receiver's Book, 1851-1860. Barcode Number 1096551 contains Receiver's Book, 1853-1896.
- Common Law Issues, 1880-1889
  This record contains issue of the Common Law Court.
- Execution Book, Volume B, 1883-1924
  This book is a record of executions.
- Fee Books, 1871-1899 (bulk 1871-1881)
  Barcode Number 1096593 contains Fee Book, 1871-1881. Barcode Number 1096594 contains Fee Book, 1883-1889. Barcode Number 1096592 contains Fee Book, 1893-1899.
- Chancery Fee Book, 1893-1899
  This book records the fees collected for Chancery Causes.